Today's דף Daf כ"ז chaf-zayin and we continue we had just been
learning about whether מים ראשונים mayim rishonim whether it requires to be
actually poured the requirement of כח גברא koach gavra
and we pick up about fifteen lines down
ואמר רבא v'amar rava line starts with the word נוטלין. notlin. ואמר
רבא v'amar rava and רבא Rava says כלי שאין בו רביעית אין
נוטלין ממנו לידים kli she'ein bo revi'is ein notlin mimenu l'yadayim that
if the vessel you're using to pour the water so here's the
requirement of a vessel does not have a container רביעית revi'is which
is about three and a half ounces you can't use it for
נטילת ידים. netilas yadayim. So the גמרא Gemara says איני eini ואמר
רבא כלי שאינו מחזיק רביעית אין נוטלין ממנו לידים v'amar rava kli
she'eino machzik revi'is ein notlin mimenu l'yadayim we have another version of
רבא's Rava statement that says that a vessel that cannot hold a
רביעית revi'is you can't use. So the first one said it doesn't
have a רביעית revi'is in it which means the amount of liquid
required to be in the vessel is a רביעית revi'is here it
says that the vessel has to be able to contain a רביעית.
revi'is. So that suggests המחזיק hamachzik if it can hold a רביעית
revi'is if that's the volume of the vessel אף על גב דלית
ביה af al gav d'leis bei even if the amount of liquid
is not that much it's okay. So first of all you have
to imagine the scenario here you are using it's a size of
a first of all we're demanding a certain size vessel regardless of
how much liquid is in it which clearly says that you need
something called a כלי kli a vessel and since a רביעית revi'is
is considered to be sort of a minimum amount of liquid less
than that would not be considered a significant vessel so here's the
requirement of כלי. kli. Actually according to some ראשונים Rishonim the reason
the ברכה beracha is על נטילת ידים al netilas yadayim the word
נטילה netila can mean to take the hand but also a נטלא
natla is the Aramaic for a vessel for a כלי kli so
therefore the כלי kli is certainly central and here we have this
vessel that's the right size but has less than a רביעית revi'is
of liquid in it so less than three and a half ounces
and you're going to use this to wash both hands which is
pretty amazing if you think about that about how much water it's
saying is really required on each hand maybe that is to support
for the earlier version that really is talking about like the just
the fingers or the tops of the fingers anyway so that's what
we're saying that it seems like the vessel is enough even if
you don't have that amount of liquid in it. So the גמרא
Gemara answers לא קשיא הא לחד הא לתרי lo kashya ha l'chad
ha l'trei it's not difficult the difference is whether it's one person
doing it or two people doing it and meaning that it needs
to start as we'll see with a רביעית revi'is of liquid but
after it had that and it was
one it was used for נטילת ידים netilas yadayim the second person
can use it even when it has less than a רביעית revi'is
because it came from originally a רביעית revi'is that was used for
נטילת ידים netilas yadayim דתניא d'tanya we taught in the ברייתא Barisa
מי רביעית נוטלין לידים לאחד ואפילו לשנים mei revi'is notlin l'yadayim l'echad
v'afillu l'shnayim if the water is a רביעית revi'is you can use
it for נטילת ידים netilas yadayim for one person and even for
two people which is again really amazing now two people are using
just three and a half ounces of water for a נטילת ידים
netilas yadayim but the point being for us that the second person
can do it even if it's less than a רביעית revi'is as
long as it started with a רביעית revi'is which was originally used
for
נטילת ידים. netilas yadayim. אמר ליה רב ששת לאמימר amar lei Rav
Sheshes l'Amemar קפדיתו אמנא kapdisu amana do you care about the vessel?
Now that we've introduced the idea that not only it's an amount
of liquid but that the vessel has to contain a certain amount
so there are criteria for the vessel so now he's saying does
it really matter about the vessel the way רש"י Rashi explains it
is does the vessel have to be whole let's say it's a
broken vessel? אמר ליה אין amar lei in yes אחזותא achazusa do
you care about what the appearance whether it looks like water? Remember
before we said very hot water or hot water might not be
good that's certain type of definitions of what constitutes acceptable water so
what if it's like cloudy or it's not clear water? אמר ליה
אין amar lei in yes there also is a requirement that it
has an appearance of water. אשיעורא ashi'ura how about a minimum quantity
a רביעית revi'is which is what we've just been discussing of the
water? אמר ליה אין amar lei in yes איכא דאמרי ika d'amri
some say הכי אמר ליה hachi amar lei this is how he
responded אמנא ואחזותא קפדינן amana v'achazusa kapdinan I care about the vessel
and about the appearance of the water אשיעורא לא קפדינן ashi'ura lo
kapdinan I don't care about the actual amount of liquid so maybe
the vessel has to be able to hold that much but you
don't need a רביעית revi'is and this is consistent with what we
said before in a scenario where it was originally started that way
דתניא d'tanya we taught in the ברייתא Barisa or דתנן d'tnan really
it should be in a משנה Mishnah מי רביעית נוטלין לידים לאחד
ואפילו לשנים mei revi'is notlin l'yadayim l'echad v'afillu l'shnayim you do you
can use for נטילת ידים netilas yadayim for one person a רביעית
revi'is and even for two people. So here originally so here it's
being brought out as evidence that you don't even have to start
with a רביעית revi'is that you don't even need a שיעור shiur
at all like the גמרא Gemara had originally maybe suggested and now
the גמרא Gemara reconciles it with the earlier discussion ולא היא v'lo
hi it's not true שאני התם משום דקאתי משירי טהרה shani hasam
mishum d'ka'asi mishirei tahara there it's different because it comes from the
remnant of טהרה tahara purity. So if it started with a רביעית
revi'is and that רביעית revi'is was used not for drinking but the
original רביעית revi'is was used for נטילת ידים netilas yadayim and there's
something left over then it is water that is fit for טהרה
tahara purposes it was part of water that was used for נטילת
ידים netilas yadayim that started with a רביעית revi'is so therefore this
remnant is enough again suggesting that you can get through נטילת ידים
netilas yadayim with a very small amount of liquid. It gets to
whole questions about whether you have to do it once or twice,
how much of the hand, and so on. It's a little hard
to imagine the full scenario here unless you sort of speak about
the fingertips and you know a very minimal- and maybe even only
pouring once. Okay,
now the גמרא Gemara goes on and says like this. אשכחן רב
יעקב מנהר פקוד Askin Rav Yaakov min Nehar Pakod נטלא, natla, he
took a נטלא, natla, notice the word נטלא natla like נטילת ידים,
Netilas Yadayim, of a vessel בת רביעיתא. bas revi'isa. So he established
in נהר פקוד Nehar Pakod a vessel, רש''י Rashi says that this
means a glass vessel that would hold a רביעית. Revi'is. So that
was like the standard רביעית Revi'is measure, and he would do that
so people could determine and use that to determine whether their vessels
were big enough to use for נטילת ידים. Netilas Yadayim. So that
was his sort of like bureau of standards. This was the definition.
You would measure against it. It's not just like if you know
for פסח, Pesach, you know, they have these like mats, these plastic
laminated mats. You could figure out so you have enough מצה, Matzah,
do you have enough כרפס. Karpas. So already in that time they
had standard שיעור shiur measures and people could determine if it held
a רביעית Revi'is or not for the vessel for נטילת ידים. Netilas
Yadayim. Interestingly, it would also be relevant for things like for קידוש
Kiddush and so on. Okay, now the גמרא Gemara goes on. אשכחן
רב אשי בהוצל, Askin Rav Ashi be-Hutzal, רב אשי Rav Ashi in
בהוצל behu-Hutzal made a similar thing and he established כוזא בת רביעיתא.
kuza bas revi'isa. A כוזא, kuza, which is also a vessel, but
it's a pottery vessel, also that held a רביעית. Revi'is. That was
the standard of measurement. People could check it. Presumably it wasn't only
helpful but it was a standard but also that people then it
got the message across that you needed a רביעית. Revi'is. ואמר רבא,
V'amar Rava, רבא Rava also says, מגופת חבית שתיקנה נוטלין ממנה לידים.
Magufas chavitz she-tiknah notlin mimena le-yadayim. So now that we've mentioned a
vessel matters, don't think it has to be some big fancy vessel.
If you take a stopper for a barrel, for like a wine
barrel, apparently those like a big large stopper, and you cut out
a, you know, a hole in it, a crevice, and an indent,
and then you could now contain enough liquid, you can even use
that for your כוס kos for נטילת ידים. Netilas Yadayim.
חמתא וכפיזא שתיקנן נוטלין מהן לידים. Cheimasa d'kifiza she-tiknan notlin mehen le-yadayim.
Similarly, a type of a flask, a water skin, that you fixed,
you can use for נטילת ידים. Netilas Yadayim. Not clear to me
exactly why you have to fix it. They actually hold leather. They
hold water, liquid naturally. Maybe because if the hole was very small
the water would only dribble out. Anyway, you can use those things
as well. איבעיא להו: Ibaya lehu: מהו לאכול במפה? mahu lechol b'mappa?
Now we get to a very, I'm sorry, I skipped a line.
שק וקופה אע''פ שמקבלין אין נוטלין מהם לידים. Sak v'kuppa af al
pi d'mekablin ein notlin mehem le-yadayim. There are some things which are
defined as not considered sort of vessels, sort of like cups, even
if functionally they can do that. Let's say you have a sack
used for keeping let's say I don't know wheat in it, or
let's say you have a box, you know, you can't use that
for נטילת ידים Netilas Yadayim even though physically, you know, they contain,
they have a place where you can, which will hold the liquid.
Those are not considered to be basically types of liquid vessels and
therefore cannot be used. Their primary function is for something else. So
that raises interesting questions of exactly how you'd draw the line. Let's
say you're in a place that they don't have a cup for
נטילת ידים, Netilas Yadayim, can you use some random thing that can
basically just hold the liquid in it?
I don't know, could you use a shoe? And that would be
actually disgusting. But anyway, here are the questions about it's not just
functional, it has to be defined as a proper vessel with a
certain amount of latitude in terms of what constitutes a vessel,
but not everything. Now the גמרא Gemara goes on, איבעיא להו, ibaya
lehu, they raise the question: מהו לאכול במפה? mahu lechol b'mappa? Ah,
here's a great question, right, what the kids always ask. Can't we
just not hold onto the bread? I don't know, my kids ask
it anyway, whatever. You know, why do we, let's not do נטילת
ידים, Netilas Yadayim, we just won't touch the bread with our hands.
So can you wrap the bread in a napkin or wrap your
hands in a napkin since the only concern was with touching. Now
one thing you have to be aware of, which is going to
come up also on the עמוד ב, amud beis, is that while
it is a concern of communicating טומאה, tumah, it was only in
the context of eating. So for example, you can handle the bread,
you can make sandwiches, you don't have to do נטילת ידים Netilas
Yadayim even though logically if it was a world of טומאה וטהרה
tumah v'taharah that would be a problem. They only made the requirement
in the context of eating. So touching by itself is not alone,
you have to eat. Now the גמרא Gemara is asking the reverse
question. Let's say you're eating without touching. What would the story be
there? Can you get out of this? Or is the experience of
eating always require נטילת ידים? Netilas Yadayim? So that's the question. מהו?
Mahu? So מהו? mahu? איבעיא להו: Ibaya lehu: לאכול במפה מהו? lechol
b'mappa mahu? מי חיישינן דילמא נגע ביה? mi-chashinan dilma naga lei? So
the way it's phrasing it here is not as a formal question:
Do we always say it for eating? But it's actually phrasing it
as a practical question: Are we concerned that inadvertently you will come
to touch it or not? Which we will see later the possibility
that even if we're not concerned, it still is just anybody who
eats bread has to wash hands. But anyway, here it's phrased as
practically would we demand washing hands because you might inadvertently touch it.
the bread even if your hands or the bread is wrapped in
some type of an napkin. So what's the story? תא
שמע, Tashma, come and hear. כשנתנו לו לרבי צדוק, Keshenatnu lo l'Rabbi
Tzaddok, here you are coming up to סוכות, Sukkot, famous משנה Mishnah
by סוכה Sukkah talking about how much stuff you have to eat
in the סוכה. Sukkah. So when they gave food to רבי צדוק,
Rabbi Tzaddok, אכל פחות מכביצה, achal pachot m'kabeitzah,
he ate less than a כביצה kabeitzah of this food,
ונטלו
במפה, un'talo b'mapah, he took it in a מפה mapah in a
cloth, ואכלו חוץ לסוכה, v'achalo chutz lasukkah, and he ate it outside
the סוכה. Sukkah. So the first point is that bread less than
a כביצה, kabeitzah, you don't go by כזית, kezayit, less than a
כביצה kabeitzah does not have to be eaten in the סוכה Sukkah
according to this.
And he did not wash his hands, presumably that was because he
wrapped it up in a cloth. ולא בירך אחריו, V'lo beireich acharayiv,
you don't have to do ברכת המזון Birkat Hamazon also for the
same reason. Even though אכילה achilah is with a כזית, kezayit, it's
not really satisfying until you're ואכלת ושבעת v'achalta v'savata until you're talking
about a כביצה kabeitzah and the same logic would apply for eating
in a סוכה. Sukkah. It's not only the act of eating, I
mean you don't have to eat everything in a סוכה, Sukkah, it's
really the sense of a סעודה seudah which requires a greater amount.
So the כביצה kabeitzah certainly addresses the issue about the ברכת המזון
Birkat Hamazon and outside of the סוכה. Sukkah. By the way, it
does seem like a little bit, you know, a little funny like
doing all these things to avoid having to do a מצוה, mitzvah,
but anyway, maybe it was physically just difficult for him. And so
if you, so you had all of this at less than a
כביצה, kabeitzah, got out of the סוכה, Sukkah, got out of benching,
and he didn't wash his hands because he wrapped it. So the
question is does the כביצה, kabeitzah, does the size also factor into
why he did not wash his hands? Let's take a look. מאי
לאו, Mai lav, does this not suggest הכביצה בעי נטילת ידים hakabeitzah
ba'ei netilat yadayim that once it was the full size of a
כביצה kabeitzah you'd have to wash your hands and the only reason
he didn't was because it was smaller. Now again that's quite fascinating,
right? Because it's not just touching, it's eating bread that requires, and
maybe we're saying it's the same logic, maybe only if you're eating
bread, not just a simple act of eating but really a sense
of a סעודה, seudah, and a סעודה seudah requires at least a
כביצה. kabeitzah. So maybe the reason he didn't have to do it
was because of the size and that's why he did not wash
the hands, but wrapping would not have been enough, the wrapping was
extraneous.
So the גמרא Gemara says דילמא Dilma no, maybe not, maybe it's
the opposite. הכביצה בעי סוכה וברכה, Hakabeitzah ba'ei Sukkah u'vracha, maybe the
כביצה, kabeitzah, the smaller size addressed the issue of the סוכה Sukkah
and the ברכת המזון. Birkat Hamazon. So if it was a כביצה
kabeitzah size it would not need, then it would need a סוכה,
Sukkah, would need a ברכת המזון. Birkat Hamazon. But it was the
fact that it was wrapped that got him out of having to
do נטילת ידים. netilat yadayim. It actually a little bit sounds that
way or else why mention the fact that the food was wrapped?
So this case is inconclusive, but it actually could be read that
it had to do with the size of the food, which raises
the question what size of bread you need to do נטילת ידים
netilat yadayim for, and it also gets certainly to the issue and
whether the wrapping was itself sufficient to get out of doing נטילת
ידים. netilat yadayim. Now I should mention that להלכה l'halacha there are
opinions that actually say that you do need, that you do not
do נטילת ידים netilat yadayim if it's less than a כביצה kabeitzah
based on the suggestion of this. Now I've explained it because נטילת
ידים's netilat yadayim connection to סעודה seudah and the role of a
כביצה kabeitzah with the סעודה. seudah. However, להלכה l'halacha we פוסק posek
you do ברכת המזון Birkat Hamazon on less than a כביצה, kabeitzah,
you do ברכת המזון Birkat Hamazon on a כזית, kezayit, although most
say that that's only דרבנן d'rabbanan because you would need a כביצה
kabeitzah for ברכת המזון דאורייתא Birkat Hamazon d'Oraita because of that aspect
of שביעה. seviyah. So therefore, it seems that at least you do
ברכת המזון Birkat Hamazon for a כזית, kezayit, most say that you
do נטילת ידים netilat yadayim also for a כזית. kezayit. There is
however an opinion that no, that you need a כביצה kabeitzah either
for the reason that I suggested that that's a real שיעור shiur
of a סעודה, seudah, although then it wouldn't be consistent with our
ruling by ברכת המזון, Birkat Hamazon, or because even for being able
to become טמא tamei something would have to be the size of
a כביצה kabeitzah at least מדאורייתא m'd'Oraita in order to become טמא.
tamei. So for, there is some discussion להלכה l'halacha do you do
נטילת ידים netilat yadayim when it's between a כזית kezayit and a
כביצה. kabeitzah. Our practice is that at least משנה ברורה Mishnah Berurah
says that if it's less than a כביצה kabeitzah you would do
it without a ברכה, bracha, although certainly there are many that do
it with a ברכה bracha as soon as it is a כזית
kezayit or more. Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara goes on about
this question about what happens if the hands or the bread is
wrapped. תא שמע Tashma come and hear, ושמואל אשכחיה לרב דקאכיל במפה.
U'Shmuel ashkechei l'Rav d'ka-achal b'mapah. שמואל Shmuel found רב, Rav, his colleague,
that was eating with a, you know the bread wrapped. אמר ליה,
Amar leih, and he assumed that he hadn't washed his hands. אמר
ליה, Amar leih, עבדין כדין? Avdin kadein? Is this how you act?
That you wrap your hands and you don't do נטילת ידים? netilat
yadayim? Obviously indicating that שמואל Shmuel thought it was not acceptable. אמר
ליה, Amar leih, and רב Rav sent back to him, דעתי קצרה
עלי. Da'ati katzra alay. No no no, it has nothing to do
with not washing my hands, it's just that I'm finicky and I
don't like to handle the bread directly so I wrap it, but
of course I did נטילת ידים. netilat yadayim. So according to this,
שמואל Shmuel and by רב's Rav response רב Rav as well, both
are of the opinion that even if it is wrapped you need
to do נטילת ידים. netilat yadayim. כי סליק
רבי זירא, Ki silik Rabbi Zeira, when רבי זירא Rabbi Zeira went
to ארץ ישראל, Eretz Yisrael, אשכחינהו לרבי אמי ולרבי אסי, ashkecheinhu l'Rabbi
Ammi u'l'Rabbi Assi, he found רבי אמי Rabbi Ammi and רבי אסי.
Rabbi Assi. דקא אכלי בבלאי חמטוטי deka achlei be-balai chamtutei that they
were eating with their bread with sort of
wrapped rags, worn out rags, worn out things that were used for
worn out flax, whatever, like water skins.
So, and he assumed also that they were not doing נטילת ידים,
Netilat Yadayim, they were doing this as an alternative to נטילת ידים.
Netilat Yadayim. אמר, Amar, so he said, תרי גבי רברבי כוותייכו, Trei
gavi raberavi kevaseichu, two great rabbis like you,
ריתו בדרב ושמואל, ritu de-Rav u-Shmuel, you're making a mistake in a
position that's held by רב Rav and שמואל? Shmuel? רב Rav and
שמואל Shmuel we see from the previous story both held that you
still have to do נטילת ידים. Netilat Yadayim. So, הא דעתי קצרה
קאמר, ha da'ati katzara ka'amar, so when רב Rav was actually challenged,
he said that it was because he was finicky and it had
nothing and he wasn't doing it as an alternative. So both רב
Rav and שמואל Shmuel are of the opinion that even if the
bread is wrapped, it requires נטילת ידים. Netilat Yadayim. אשתמיטתיה, Ishtmiteih, הא
דאמר רב תחליפא בר אבימי אמר שמואל, ha de-amar Rav Tachlifa bar
Avimi amar Shmuel, התירו מפה לאוכלי תרומה ולא התירו מפה לאוכלי טהרות.
hitiru mappa le-ochlei terumah ve-lo hitiru mappa le-ochlei taharos. רבי אמי Rabbi
Ami and רבי אסי, Rabbi Assi, כהני הוו. kohanim havu. So he
actually forgot or erred in the point that we actually say, somewhat
ironically, that in the name of שמואל, Shmuel, that you are allowed
to wrap your hands if you're eating תרומה, terumah, if you're eating
real תרומה terumah when you really have a problem of your hands
being טמא, tamei, then it's okay if the food is wrapped or
your hand is wrapped without נטילת ידים. Netilat Yadayim. They did not
allow the wrapping for people that are eating non-תרומה non-terumah like us,
eating normal
bread and are just washing our hands for that ritual. Now why?
The real serious case is the תרומה terumah case. But the point
being that if it's תרומה terumah and it is that serious and
the people eating it are כהנים kohanim who are very punctilious about
laws of טומאה tumah and טהרה, taharah, then they will be careful.
And רבי אמי Rabbi Ami and רבי אסי Rabbi Assi were כהנים
kohanim and were eating תרומה. terumah. Again, it's interesting, right, תרומה בזמן
הזה, terumah be-zman hazeh,
which is a debate if it's דאורייתא, de-oraisa, דרבנן, de-rabbanan, or whatever,
but they were still eating it as כהנים kohanim and therefore they
were allowed to wrap their hands. תרומה terumah being eaten by כהנים,
kohanim, they're going to be punctilious, it's very weighty, they're going to
be careful, that's okay. But for us, when we wash it just
before bread, then we cannot use the alternative of wrapping the hands.
All right, איבעיא להו, ibaya lehu, they raised the question.
By the way, I should mention that in yesterday's שיעור shiur we
also mentioned the idea that somebody might be כהן kohen and demand
more for תרומה, terumah, and I actually misspoke because there also by
קרבנות korbonos obviously are not nowadays, but תרומה terumah is, at least
דרבנן rabbinically if not biblically, so therefore you do have the scenario
of really washing the hands for תרומה terumah that was mentioned back
there. However, I should still say though that the problem is
that gets rid of the דרבנן rabbinic problems of the hands, it
does not get rid of the טומאת מת tumas meis problem, and
as a general rule all of us even כהנים kohanim are assumed
to be טמאים tameiyim with טומאת מת. tumas meis. So maybe somehow
they weren't making that assumption in the time here of the גמרא,
Gemara, but it definitely and therefore nowadays nobody will eat the תרומה
terumah even in ארץ ישראל, Eretz Yisrael, but at least in the
time of the גמרא Gemara it seemed like they really were eating
תרומה terumah at least דרבנן. rabbinically. So at least in the גמרא
Gemara though they were eating תרומה terumah and following the laws of
טומאה וטהרה, tumah ve-taharah, so apparently they were not considered טמאי מת
tmei meis or have some way of addressing that, whatever, meaning okay,
they weren't considered טמאי מת. tmei meis. Anyway,
so that's why they were doing it, because they were eating real
תרומה, terumah, but normally you are not allowed to wrap the hands
as an alternative. So that seems to be the conclusion. So now
that we're saying you can't wrap the hands, before we said maybe
it was a concern that you might accidentally touch, but now we're
going to see that the גמרא Gemara is really turning to the
issue about maybe there's just a formal requirement that anybody eating bread
and it really matters and you know irrespective of whether touch even
is a concern or not. So let's take a look. איבעיא להו,
ibaya lehu, they raised the question, אוכל מחמת מאכיל צריך נטילת ידים
או לא. Ochal machmas machal tzarich netilat yadayim o lo. If you're
eating because somebody is feeding you, somebody is putting the bread directly
in your mouth, do you need נטילת ידים? Netilat Yadayim? And this
is a great example where forget it, no concern that you might
touch, I guess you could theoretically raise that as an issue, but
it really seems that the question is maybe the same way touching
without eating does not require, eating without touching even if touching is
not a concern at all does require. That is just formally where
they demanded נטילת ידים, Netilat Yadayim, although it does seem a little
ironic. So what's the story? או לא, O lo, תא שמע, tashma,
come and hear, דרב הונא בר סחורה הוי קאי קמיה דרב המנונא.
de-Rav Huna bar Sachorah havi kai kemei de-Rav Hamnuna. רב הונא בר
סחורה Rav Huna bar Sachorah was sort of standing in front of,
but here it means attending to, serving רב המנונא, Rav Hamnuna, בלמיה
אומצא, balmeih umtza, he sort of fed him meat, ואכל, ve-achal, and
he ate it. Now of course there's no bread here, but we
have to assume that this means with accompanying bread.
אמר ליה, Amar lei, אי לאו דרב המנונא את, ilav de-Rav Hamnuna
at, if you were not רב המנונא Rav Hamnuna and you were
such a great person, לא ספינא לך. lo sefina lach. I would
not have fed you without allowing you to, without your doing the
נטילת ידים. netilas yadayim. מאי טעמא, mai ta'ama, why? לאו משום דזהיר
ולא נגע? lav mishum d'zahir v'lo naga? Doesn't it mean that look,
you are רב המנונא, Rav Hamnuna, I can trust that you're not
going to touch the bread? So you don't need נטילת ידים netilas
yadayim and I can feed you without doing נטילת ידים, netilas yadayim,
which means that in scenarios where we can trust or assume that
somebody will not touch the bread and somebody else is feeding them
and they're not handling it, then actually we would not need נטילת
ידים. netilas yadayim. Actually this is more relevant than it would seem.
It asks the question somebody's in a hospital, let's say, and actually
is being fed by one of the nurses, is there still a
concept of נטילת ידים netilas yadayim if somebody is eating bread? So
the גמרא Gemara says it seems like the answer would be, at
least under some circumstances, you would not need to. And that's what
was going on there. So the גמרא Gemara says: לא דזריז קדים
ומשי ידיה מעיקרא. lo d'zaris kadim umashi yadei me'ikara. It doesn't mean
he was careful not to touch. It means if you were not
רב המנונא Rav Hamnuna and had not already been, you know, had
the alacrity to go ahead and wash your hands ahead of time.
So he was actually saying, if it were somebody else, they wouldn't
think to have washed their hands, but you knew to wash your
hands ahead of time, and that's why I can go ahead and
feed you. So according to that, the conclusion actually is you do
have to wash your hands. So the גמרא Gemara has not concluded
that. תא שמע, ta shema, come and hear. דאמר רבי זירא אמר
רב, d'amar Rabbi Zeira amar Rav, said רבי זירא Rabbi Zeira in
the name of רב: Rav: לא יתן אדם פרוסה לתוך פיו של
שמש אלא אם כן יודע בו שנטל ידיו. lo yitein adam prusa
l'soch piv shel shamash ela im kein yodeia bo shenatal yadav.
You have here your waiter serving you at the meal and he's,
you know, and every now and then he's handling all this delicious
food, so you might want, feel bad for him, give him some
of the food to eat, so pop it into his mouth. Don't
pop a piece of bread into his mouth unless you know he
did נטילת ידים. netilas yadayim. So here you see very clearly, even
if somebody's being fed, they still need to do נטילת ידים. netilas
yadayim. והשמש מברך על כל כוס וכוס ואינו מברך על כל פרוסה
ופרוסה. v'hashamash mevarech al kol kos v'chos v'eino mevarech al kol prusa
u'prusa. Anytime anybody offers him a drink of wine from the table,
he has to make a new ברכה bracha because normally people wouldn't
offer him a drink of wine, so every new offer is unexpected
and therefore he has to make a new ברכה. bracha. But people
do regularly offer him pieces of bread and therefore he did not
does not have to make multiple ברכות, brachos, he can assume he's
going to get other pieces of bread. ורבי יוחנן אמר מברך על
כל פרוסה ופרוסה. v'Rabbi Yochanan amar mevarech al kol prusa u'prusa. And
רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan said no, even that he can't be confident
of and he has to make another ברכה bracha for every piece
of bread. אמר רב פפא, amar Rav Papa, so רב פפא Rav
Papa said: בשלמא דרב ודרבי יוחנן לא קשיא. bishlama d'Rav u'd'Rabbi Yochanan
lo kashya. I understand that debate. הא דאיכא אדם חשוב והא דליכא
אדם חשוב. ha d'ika adam chashuv v'ha d'leika adam chashuv. Not only
do I understand the debate, but I'm actually going to reconcile the
debate. And I will say, if there's an important person at the
table, you want to demonstrate your generosity, so then you're going to
more regularly give some food to your waiter who is there. And
then he can assume he's going to get more bread, not necessarily
wine, but more bread, and he doesn't have to make a ברכה
bracha every new time. If there's no important person at the table,
you won't go out of your way to be nice to the
waiter necessarily, and therefore every even new offer of bread is unexpected
and cannot be counted on and requires a new ברכה. bracha. That's
how to reconcile that. Fine, that was the ישוב yishuv about making
a ברכה. bracha.
מכל מקום, mi'kol makom, but regarding our question: הכא קאמר אלא אם
כן יודע בו שנטל ידיו. hacha ka'amar ela im kein yodeia bo
shenatal yadav. You can't feed the waiter unless he did נטילת ידים.
netilas yadayim. So you see very clearly that even somebody not handling
it has to do נטילת ידים netilas yadayim as long as they're
eating it. So the גמרא Gemara says: לא, שאני שמש דטריד. lo,
shani shamash d'tarid. The שמש shamash might be different, the waiter might
be different, he's so distracted all the time that he's handling so
many things, that there he might require it because there, even if
he's being fed, he might handle it. But somebody else who we
can be confident won't handle it, that maybe would not have to
do נטילת ידים. netilas yadayim. So this actually is the perfect question
for the גמרא. Gemara. Meaning, it's one thing if the bread is
wrapped, you might say we need נטילת ידים, netilas yadayim, but that
could be because we're concerned that it might be touched. What if
somebody's being fed in a scenario where there's no concern of being
touched? So the waiter maybe we're concerned he'll touch it, he would
do נטילת ידים. netilas yadayim. But if somebody's being fed with no
concern, would we still demand נטילת ידים? netilas yadayim? That is a
question about is it just about eating regardless of touching, or is
it only when there is some possible concern of touching? So the
גמרא Gemara has still not really concluded it. Let's keep on going.
איבעיא להו, iba'ya lehu, excuse me, I skipped one. תנו רבנן, tanu
rabanan, as our Rabbis taught: לא יתן אדם פרוסה לשמש בין שהכוס
בידו בין שהכוס ביד בעל הבית. lo yitein adam prusa l'shamash bein
shehakos b'yado bein shehakos b'yad ba'al habayis. Do not give bread to
the שמש shamash whether you are—you have a cup of wine in
your hand or whether the בעל הבית ba'al habayis has a cup
of wine in his hand. Why? If you remember the גמרא Gemara
before talked about doing things during the meal when somebody is drinking,
that it might not be to their liking and then they'll start
choking on what they're drinking. So there's a similar concern here. You're
giving bread to the שמש, shamash, the בעל הבית ba'al habayis might
not want you to share from your food to the waiter, he'll
get upset, he's drinking, or you'll get upset and you're drinking but
you'll see he's upset and it'll cause you to choke or it'll
cause things to be spilled. So don't do that. שמא יארע דבר
קלקלה בסעודה, shema yeira davar kalla bas'uda, maybe there'll be some accident
and problem because of his—the בעל הבית ba'al habayis will be upset
about what you're doing.
והשמש—so v'hashamash fine, that was—that was not directly relevant for us. והשמש
שלא נטל ידיו אסור ליתן לו. v'hashamash shelo natal yadav asur litein
lo. and if a שמש shamash did not do נטילת ידים, netilas
yadayim, you can't feed him. So again, even though he's being fed,
he has to do it, but we said that might be because
he will be he is distracted and will easily touch. איבעיא להו.
Iba'ya lehu. מואכיל צריך נטילת ידים או אינו צריך? Mo'achil tzarich netilas
yadayim o eino tzarich? How about the feeder, not the feedee? So
here's somebody handling bread, normal handling bread does not require נטילת ידים,
netilas yadayim, but here you're handling bread and it is being eaten,
and there's an act of eating going on. You're just not eating
it; you are feeding it. Is that enough considered like the idea
of eating bread that requires נטילת ידים netilas yadayim or not? It
is being eaten and you are handling it and feeding it. Do
you, the feeder, have to do נטילת ידים? netilas yadayim? תא שמע,
Ta shema, come and hear, דתני דבי מנשה, Detani devei Menashe, we
taught in the house of מנשה, Menashe, רבן שמעון בן גמליאל אומר:
Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel omer: אשה מדיחה ידה אחת במים ונותנת פת
לבנה קטן. Isha medicha yadah achas bamayim venosenes pas livnah katan. This
is about יום כיפור, Yom Kippur, that
even though you're not allowed to wash your hands on יום כיפור,
Yom Kippur, if a woman is feeding her child, she can wash
one of her hands, she doesn't need to use both, and give
the bread to her child. אמרו עליו, Amru alav, and they said
on him, על שמאי הזקן, al Shammai ha-Zaken, on the elder שמאי,
Shammai, שלא רצה להאכיל בידו אחת, shelo ratza le-ha'achil beyado achas, that
he was so careful, oh, I'm not going to violate יום כיפור,
Yom Kippur, I'm not going to wash my hands to feed my
kids, and that was overly stringent. וגזרו עליו, Vegozru alav, so they
in order to show him that, you know, you know, it's not
that some that there's you have to sometimes make certain trade-offs for
because part of your religious obligations is also your obligations to others,
וגזרו עליו, vegozru alav, שיאכיל בשתי ידיו. sheya'achil bishtei yadav. He has
to use both his hands to feed his kids and on יום
כיפור Yom Kippur would have to do נטילת ידים netilas yadayim with
both his hands. Anyway, what do you see? You see that we
are allowing the washing of the hands for a feeder on יום
כיפור. Yom Kippur. So presumably this is the rabbinic requirement of washing
hands. Interesting the idea of just one hand, which we'll bracket for
now, but here you see that as a feeder you do have
to wash your hands. אמר אביי, Amar Abaye, אביי Abaye said, no,
that's not what's going on there. התם משום שיבצא. Hasam mishum shivtza.
That is because of this evil spirit, this שיבצא, shivtza, right? Remember
before we had אביי Abaye telling a whole series of things that
he first wasn't, you know, did not interpret things around the spirit
world, but רבא Rava set him straight. So anyway, he says that
that's what's going on here, that if you do not do נטילת
ידים netilas yadayim in the morning, then there's this evil spirit on
your hands. Right? The reason we do נטילת ידים netilas yadayim in
the morning, the גמרא Gemara gives two reasons. I mean, one is
more just as a way of symbolizing we're sort of starting the
day and we're going to תפילה tefilla and we're starting the day
to serve God, so we do נטילת ידים, netilas yadayim, but also
this understanding that there is a spirit that rests on the hands
in the morning after having slept and therefore you need to do
the נטילת ידים netilas yadayim in order to get the spirit away.
So אביי Abaye said that's why they were washing their hands; they're
handling food, they didn't want the spirit to attach to the food
and make the food, you know, dangerous to be eaten. It is
not the ritual נטילת ידים netilas yadayim of the eating of bread.
So we cannot prove anything from that. תא שמע, Ta shema, come
and hear, דאבוה דשמואל אשכחיה לשמואל, De'avuhu di-Shmuel ashkechei li-Shmuel,
so the father of שמואל Shmuel found שמואל, Shmuel, remember שמואל Shmuel
is the one who said wrapping still requires נטילת ידים, netilas yadayim,
so he found שמואל Shmuel דקא בכי, de-ka bachi, that he was
crying. אמר ליה, Amar lei, אמאי קא בכית, amai ka bachis, why
are you crying? So he said דמחיין רבאי, de-machyan rabbai, אמאי דאמרי
לי, amai de-amri li, כספית לבראי kasafis livrai ולא משית ידך? velo
mashis yadach?
That people are beating me up, they're giving me a hard time
because they're telling me that you fed your child and you didn't
do נטילת ידים. netilas yadayim. אמאי לא משית? Amai lo mashis?
So his father said to him, so why didn't you do נטילת
ידים? netilas yadayim? אמר ליה, Amar lei, הוא אכיל ואנא משיינא? Hu
achil va-ana mashina? What,
he's going to eat and I have to wash my hands? נטילת
ידים Netilas yadayim is only for the eater; it's not for the
feeder, it's for the one who eats. אמר ליה, Amar lei, so
his father said to him, לא מסתייא דלא גמירי, Lo mistayei delo
gemiri, it's not enough that these people don't know the הלכה, halacha,
בממך נמי מחו? bimemcha nami machu? But they're also beating you up?
Again, I don't know if it's literal or figurative, but the point
is, you know, so it's first of all they're ignorant. Second of
all, as a result of their ignorance, they're giving you a hard
time. Often that's very much the case of people that don't know,
that don't appreciate, don't understand the nuance of what's going on, and
therefore they're the ones that are always raising the cry of outrage.
Anyway, so that so clearly you see that שמואל Shmuel was of
the opinion that if you're not the eater, even if you're the
feeder, you don't have to wash your hands, which is very consistent.
So at the end of the day according to שמואל, Shmuel, it
doesn't matter if you've wrapped the bread, you still have to wash
your hands. Presumably even if you're being fed, you have to wash
your hands. It's all about the act of eating. And then the
flip side is if you're feeding, even if you're handling the bread,
you don't have to wash your hands. והלכתא, Vehilchata, and here's how
the גמרא Gemara concludes, דהלכתא אוכל מחמת מאכיל צריך נטילת ידים, Dehilchata
ochel machamas ma'achil tzarich netilas yadayim,
exactly this. If you're being fed, you have to wash your hands,
presumably even if you're certain you won't touch, but מאכיל אינו צריך
נטילת ידים, ma'achil eino tzarich netilas yadayim, the feeder does not have
to do נטילת ידים. netilas yadayim. So at the end of the
day, even though it starts in a world of טומאה וטהרה, tumah
vetahara, which is That touch and not eating, since the classic example
was eating, that's the formal way the Rabbis made the requirement, it's
somebody who eats bread, and therefore it's completely based on the eater,
not on handling is not enough, even feeding is not enough to
require, it's all based on eating. But if you are eating, even
if you're not handling, even if the bread is wrapped, and even
if someone is feeding you, you still do require נטילת ידים, netilas
yadayim, which might also touch back on the other explanation given for
it, which is, you know, the והתקדשתם והייתם קדושים ve-his-kadashtem ve-hayisem kedoshim
and somehow a sanctifying of the actual act of eating, as part
of what is going on here beyond just the טומאה tuma and
טהרה tahara concerns. So with that we end the discussion of מים
ראשונים mayim rishonim and מים אחרונים, mayim acharonim, which was all a
big digression, if you remember, from the idea of separation between meat
and milk. And now we return to the separation of meat and
milk. We've learned that they cannot be on the same table, and
that led to all discussions about eating one right after the other.
And now we're going to continue with the issue of them being
on the same table. Let's take a look. משנה: mishna: צורר אדם
בשר וגבינה במטפחת אחת ובלבד שלא יהיו נוגעים זה בזה. tzorer adam
basar u-gevina be-mitpachas achas u-vilvad she-lo yihyu nogim zeh va-zeh. You
are actually allowed to
wrap, place your meat and your cheese in one handkerchief, as long
as they don't touch. So depending on how you wrap them, you
know, on other sides of the handkerchief or whatever, but you wrap
them in a way that they're not touching, it's not a problem.
So this is ironic, right? On the same table you can't have,
but wrapping up you are allowed to do even though they're sitting
right next to each other, as long as they don't touch. If
they touch, something will transfer. Now why is it that we make
it that different? So it could be practically, right? If you're eating
you'll inadvertently come to eat things that are next to you, whereas
here you're not eating so we're not concerned. That's certainly the simplest
explanation. But it's also possible as I've been saying that the whole
idea of being at the same table is redefined, is a way
of defining what does it mean to eat together. And it's the
rabbinic problem of eating them together. So this, which is not part
of eating, is totally okay, the same way it was okay to
have them next to each other on a table that you were
taking from to put on the table, to put on the eating
table. Anything that is not in the context of eating directly is
not a problem. Okay so that's the first teaching, very much against
what they do for me when I go to the butcher, which
is that if I buy cheese and meat they make sure to
put them into separate plastic bags even though everything is already wrapped
three dozen times in its own plastic. But certainly there's no requirement,
but it makes people feel better. Okay anyway, that's the first teaching.
Then, רבן שמעון בן גמליאל אומר שני אכסנאים אוכלין על שולחן אחד
זה בשר וזה גבינה ואין חוששים. Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel omer shenei
achsanaim ochlin al shulchan echad zeh basar vezeh gevina ve-ein chosheshin. He
now comes to voice a limit to the problem of eating at
the same table. He says if you have two אכסנאים, achsanaim, two
like guests, meaning not people that know each other, two relative
strangers sitting at the same table, one can eat meat and one
can eat milk and there's no concern. Since they're strangers we're not
concerned that you'll inadvertently either offer or take from the other person's
plate. Okay, that's רבן שמעון בן גמליאל. Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel. Let's
take a look at the גמרא. Gemara. So first the גמרא Gemara
says about the milk and cheese in the same wrapper, וכי נוגע
זה בזה מאי הוי? ve-chi noge'a zeh va-zeh mai havei? Who cares
if they touch? צונין בצונין הוא, tzonin be-tzonin hu, it's all cold,
nothing transfers, you need heat to transfer taste. So אמר אביי, amar
Abaye, said Abaye, נהי דקליפה לא בעי, ne-hi de-kelipa lo ba-yei, granted
they don't require קליפה, kelipa, which is removing a super thin layer.
That's something that might be required if there's actual heat even if
they're not on the fire.
But הדחה מי לא בעי? hadacha mi lo ba-yei? At least it
needs to be rinsed.
And this is that sometimes stuff is greasy, you know, and therefore
will transfer on the surface and you need to rinse it off.
So comes for example buying let's say fish from a, you know,
at a regular store, at a supermarket. So there's a whole question
of can you trust them in terms of how the fish is
identified. There was recently 10 years ago some teenage girls did a
science fair project where they found like 30% of the stuff they
did DNA typing of the fish was sold under false labels and
now recently it's becoming a bigger issue at the government level, took
10 years for some reason. Anyway, there is a lot of mislabeling
of fish, lower quality as higher quality. So there's a whole question
of identifying and buying fish
if it's been filleted. But you certainly if it has the skin
on and you see the
fins and scales or if it's tuna or salmon which is very
distinctive and you go and you buy it at the supermarket, then
the only problem is what knives they use. So you can try
to give them their special knives to use for you, sometimes they'll
do that, but also really if it's all cold, the worst case
scenario you just have to rinse it off. There's different discussions in
the אחרונים acharonim about how much rinsing is required, rinsing with scrubbing,
without scrubbing, depending on how much might transfer. But whatever transfers is
just directly on the surface. So that is this principle here that
sometimes there is greasy stuff that transfers, but that can be solved
through a form of rinse. Now the גמרא Gemara goes on to
the issue of eating at the same table. רבן שמעון בן גמליאל
אומר שני אכסנאים אוכלין על שולחן אחד. Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel omer
shenei achsanaim ochlin al shulchan echad. אמר רב חנא בר אבמי, Amar
Rav Chana bar Avmi, אמר שמואל, Amar Shmuel, לא שנו אלא שאין
מכירין זה את זה. Lo Shanu Ela she-ein Makirin Zeh et Zeh.
This permission of two of two guests eating at the same table
where not concerned they'll share is only if they do not recognize
one another,
so they're real strangers. אבל מכירים זה את זה אסור. Aval Makirin
Zeh et Zeh Assur. If they recognize one another and they're not
strangers even if they're not super buddies and friends, then it would
be forbidden. There is still the possibility that there will be some
sharing, intentional or unintentional.
תניא נמי הכי, Tanya Nami Hachi, we taught similarly: רבן שמעון בן
גמליאל אומר שני אכסנאין שנתארחו לפונדק אחד. Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel Omer
Shenei Achsanya'in she-Nitarchu le-Fundak Echad. Two strangers, two guests that happen to
the same inn, אכסנאי Achsanya'i particularly has the meaning of a guest
in an inn. Okay, so two guests that happen to the same
inn, staying at the same inn, זה בא מן הצפון וזה בא
מן הדרום, Zeh Ba min ha-Tzafon ve-Zeh Ba min ha-Darom, total strangers,
one is coming from the north, one is coming from the south.
זה בא בחתיכתו וזה בא בגבינתו, Zeh Ba be-Chatichato ve-Zeh Ba be-Gevinato,
one is bringing with him some nice piece of meat to eat,
the other is bringing with him a chunk of cheese. אוכלין על
שולחן אחד זה בשר וזה גבינה, Ochlin al Shulchan Echad Zeh Basar
ve-Zeh Gevina, they can eat on the same table, one meat and
the other milk, ואין חוששין, ve-Ein Chosheshin, and we're not concerned that
they'll come to share. ולא אסרו אלא בתפיסה אחת, ve-Lo Assru Ela
be-Tfisa Achat,
and they only forbade it when it was one תפיסה. Tfisa. תפיסה
Tfisa like
means like one grabbing. What does this mean? So it sounds like
it's like literally wrapped together. תפיסה אחת סלקא דעתך, Tfisa Achat Salka
Datach,
do you literally mean that it's only forbidden if they're literally wrapped
together? אלא כעין תפיסה אחת, Ela ke-Ein Tfisa Achat,
we mean that it's like that's in one wrapping, meaning that they
are, you know, people that are friendly with one another and there's
some sense of eating together, not that we're sharing a table but
we're actually eating quite apart from one another. But it has to
be some sense of eating together in order to be a problem,
both because it raises the issue of inadvertent sharing and the way
I'm trying to formalize it because that is considered to be a
type of eating meat and milk together. So it's not just being
at the same table, there's some sense in which they know one
another and can be said that they're eating together.
We're just going to finish this up and then I'm going to
talk a little bit about the practical הלכה Halacha and this phrase
of תפיסה אחת. Tfisa Achat. So let's keep on going. אמר ליה
רב יימר בר שלמיא לאביי, Amar lei Rav Yeimar bar Shalmiya le-Abaye,
so רב יימר בר שלמיא Rav Yeimar bar Shalmiya said to אביי:
Abaye: שני אחים ומקפידין זה על זה מהו? Shenei Achim u-Makpidin Zeh
al Zeh Mahu?
Let's say they do recognize one another, it's even a case where
they're, you know, known each other for life, they're two brothers, but
they actually are having a little feud, they're מקפידין Makpidin one on
the other, maybe specifically in the sense of that they don't share
their food with one another, you know, they've got some fight going
on and don't you dare touch my food.
Can they eat together or not?
One bread and one meat. אמר ליה, Amar lei, he said to
him, very famous phrase: יאמרו כל הסריקין אסורין וסריקי בייטוס מותרין. Yomru
Kol ha-Serikin Assurin ve-Serikei Baitos Mutarin.
So this is a way of the גמרא, Gemara, a great phrase
the גמרא Gemara uses to express its concept called לא פלוג. Lo
Plug. We don't make distinctions. Meaning, we're not going to assess every
single ruling based on the particular context and determine does it make
sense in this context or not. We're going to have some formal
rules and we're going to be consistent about them even if some
cases don't exactly fit. So that's לא פלוג, Lo Plug, we don't
make these types of distinctions. This came up because the גמרא Gemara
says in the משנה Mishna says in פסחים Psachim that you cannot
make מצה Matzah which you basically cut designs into the מצה Matzah
and make them particular shapes because the time it takes to cut
the designs when it's dough could lead to it rising before you
bake it. So there was this person בייטוס בן זונין Baitos ben
Zonin who's an interesting character who comes up a few times in
ש"ס, Shas, and he had cookie cutters. And he wanted to know,
how about me? Can I use my cookie cutters? It doesn't take
any time. So they basically said no. What? People will say all
types of designs are forbidden and the designs of בייטוס Baitos are
permissible? So we cannot allow for these types of distinctions. Now one
way of explaining that is that if we allow your case, other
people will allow other cases which don't deserve to have an exception.
And that's one reason to keep rules, that if you make one
exception then it'll just it'll open up the floodgates. The other reason
to keep it on the formal level is just because it's impossible
to create law if every case is being adjudged on its own
merits and there's not a consistent type of a standard. So this
is the idea of לא פלוג. Lo Plug. So אביי Abaye said
we can make a basic distinction between strangers and non-strangers. Okay, that
is, and then we're consistent with that.
But as soon as but we can't start saying within people that
aren't strangers, we're going to assess the degree of how friendly they
are with one another. That's way too contextual, that's not categorical, we
can't do that. So yes, even if they're having a fight, they
can't eat at the same table.
Let's keep on going. ולטעמיך, u-le-Ta'amecha, he said back to him, and
this is always the question that's asked about the cases where we
do make exceptions to the לא פלוג Lo Plug rule, to not
making exceptions. So there's an exception to the rule that we don't
make
exceptions. הא דאמר רב אסי אמר רבי יוחנן, Ha de-Amar Rav Assi
Amar Rabbi Yochanan, that which רב אסי Rav Assi says in the
name of רבי יוחנן: Rabbi Yochanan: מי שאין לו אלא חלוק אחד
מותר לכבסו בחול המועד. Mi she-Ein lo Ela Chaluk Echad Mutar le-Chabso
be-Chol ha-Moed. You can't do laundry on חול המועד, Chol ha-Moed, we
want you to get it done before יום טוב, Yom Tov, either
because of an איסור מלאכה Issur Melacha of חול המועד Chol ha-Moed
or because we want you to come into the יום טוב... Yom
Tov... looking nice. Let's say you only have one shirt. So you
did come into the יום טוב Yom Tov looking nice, but now
it's, but now it's all sweaty and dirty. Can you do laundry
on חול המועד? Chol Hamoed? So we actually do allow that person.
Ah, we're making a distinction, here we're allowing, everybody else we're not
allowing. Aren't we afraid that that's going to open up the floodgates,
we're making distinctions?
So יאמרו Yomru why not say כל הציקן אסור וציקי בייתות מותרים,
kol hatzikan assur vetzikei baytot mutarim, the same way what, we're going
to allow your, your designs in your מצה matzah and not everybody
else's. So say here too. What, you know, how could we allow
you to do your laundry and not everybody else? So if everybody
else is אסור assur you're also אסור. assur. So why here are
we making an exception if we never make exceptions? So אמר מר
בר רב אשי amar Mar bar Rav Ashi איזורו מוכיח עליו. izoro
mochiach alav. No, the גמרא Gemara says there there's an answer. מר
בר רב אשי Mar bar Rav Ashi says your איזור, izor, your
belt, proves it. What does that mean? So רש"י Rashi says because
basically if you're doing your laundry, you're doing your laundry in your
bare back. You had to strip off your shirt to do your
laundry. So everybody sees you've taken off your shirt, you've taken off
your belt that held your shirt in place and everybody, it's self-evident
why you are allowed. So an exception that is very clear why
it's an exceptional case we might allow. But other types of situations
we will not. Okay. Now back to the point here about eating
on one table.
So תוספות Tosafot points out that since the גמרא Gemara uses the
phrase כעין תפיסה אחת ke'ein tfisa achat like it's one bundle, meaning
that they know each other, although the גמרא Gemara only uses it
to say
that it allows for cases of strangers and doesn't allow when they
know one another, תוספות Tosafot says well maybe even when they know
one another it has to be this idea of like one bundle.
And if there is some type of a separation between the two,
that's okay. And that leads to a discussion in the תוספות Tosafot
and in the ראשונים Rishonim and the אחרונים Achronim about what types
of separations. There are two types of separations. One might be a
physical barrier that if I'm going to reach over my hand to
try to get a piece of your cheese or of your meat,
I'm going to bump into something and that'll stop me and then
I'll remember. So that's an actual physical barrier. And that also really
makes it like we're at two separate tables because there's something physical
between us. Others say that anything that reminds me even if it's
not physical could suffice. So therefore anything that's a difference, if there's
some type of a special thing on the table that makes me
remember, or a simpler example is if it's on a mat. So
I will do this, I'm eating at a table and people are
eating different things, so I will put underneath what I'm eating a
piece of paper or some type of a placemat and everybody else
is eating directly off of the table. That means my eating is
different from their eating, that's some type of a סימן siman that
serves as a reminder. So this idea develops based on this phrase
תפיסה אחת tfisa achat not in the גמרא, Gemara, but it becomes
a nice way to allow more latitude in this idea of not
eating on the same table. I should mention that probably one of
the things that sort of pushed it in this direction is we
have to understand that שולחן shulchan in the גמרא Gemara is not
the type of big table we all have that we all share.
In the גמרא Gemara you're referring or in the משנה Mishnah like
they would eat in Rome, that individual trays would be brought in
front of a person. And that was called a שולחן shulchan like
we find in the משנה Mishnah in פסחים Psachim when they bring
the tray the שולחן shulchan in front of him that has the
מצה matzah and and every and everything. So therefore to eat on
the same שולחן, shulchan, you're eating really like one on top of
the other, you're all both eating off of the same tray. Nowadays
that we have a big table, there's much less of a sense
that we're really eating together in that intense way and therefore some
type of a separation whether a physical barrier or just a סימן
siman could suffice and that actually is how we rule. So with
that we will end today's דף daf and we will pick up
with tomorrow's דף. daf.